Guide to the Cornelius Baldwin Hite Papers, 1711-1918 RL.10118
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cornelius Baldwin Hite papers
1711-1918
bulk
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hite, Cornelius Baldwin
RL.10118
4.6 Linear Feet 9 boxes, 2,344 items (includes 2 vols.)
Collection contains personal, business, and legal papers of Cornelius Baldwin Hite, Jr. and of his family. The material pertains largely to life in Virginia during Reconstruction, with information about social life and customs, and on prominent Virginia families, especially the Marshall family, who were related to Hite by marriage. Includes copies (1709-1711) of passages from the diary of Mrs. Alexander Spotswood, and early legal documents relating to Hardy Co., Va.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Cornelius Baldwin Hite papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1956.
Collection Overview
The Cornelius Baldwin Hite papers contains report sheets for Cornelius B. Hite, Jr., from several schools in Virginia, 1855-1860; letters from the period of the Civil War, for the most part dealing with the impact of the war on civilians in western Virginia; a large amount of material showing the effect of Reconstruction on Cornelius B. Hite, Jr., and his relatives, including descriptions of economic distress, politics, and the migration of many Virginians to the western United States. There are letters describing social life and community health in Winchester, Virginia, in the 1870s; conditions at Shenandoah Valley Academy, 1868; and a long trip to Texas, 1875-1876. Letters, 1890-1895, are to Elizabeth Augusta (Smith) Hite, mother of Cornelius Baldwin Hite, Jr., from her sisters and grandchildren.
The collection also contains legal papers of the Christman, Fravel, and Branson families from 1797; a 19th century copy of excerpts from a journal kept by Ann Butler (Brayne) Spotswood, 1709-1711; and legal papers and letters of the Gales family, 1824-1865. Miscellaneous items include six volumes of songs, poetry, and scrapbooks; bills and receipts; clippings; printed matter; and an account book, 1838-1841, and a ledger, 1839-1841, of Cornelius Baldwin Hite, Sr.
Biographical note
Cornelius Baldwin Hite was a farmer of Winchester (Frederick Co.), Va.
Hardy County (W. Va.) -- History -- Sources; Virginia -- Genealogy; Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877) -- Virginia; Virginia -- Social life and customs; Marshall family; Hite, Cornelius Baldwin; Spotswood, Ann Butler Brayne; Hite family
- Cornelius Baldwin Hite papers, 1711-1918
  - Papers, 1711-1873; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Papers, 1874-1876; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Papers, 1885-1886; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Papers, 1885-1886; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Papers, 1887-1893; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Papers, 1894-1918 and undated; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Clippings and printed material, undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Misc. papers, undated; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Bills, receipts, etc., undated; 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Journal and account book, 1838-1841 (Volume L:5726)
  - Ledger, 1839-1841 (Volume L:5727)